Eeshan Hasan

Department of Psychology, Indiana University * (615) 769-9937 *eehasan@iu.edu [Last Updated: 9/24/2023]

PERSONAL PROFILE

I adopt a joint computational and experimental approach to better understand cognitive decision making processes. I use the insights from my research to design and test interventions to improve the quality of decisions in critical environments like medical decision making and social media interactions. My research draws on developments in artificial intelligence to develop methods to understand human decision making. Conversely, I use models of human decisions to design reliable and robust artificial intelligence algorithms.

EDUCATION

08/2022 - Present Department of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Indiana University

Cognitive Science Program, Indiana University

Phd Student (GPA - 4.0/4.0)

Computational Decision Making Lab. [Advisor: Jennifer Trueblood]

08/2019 – 07/2022 Department of Psychology, Vanderbilt University

Masters in Psychological Sciences (GPA -4.0/4.0)

Computational Decision Making Lab. [Advisor: Jennifer Trueblood]

08/2013 – 05/2018 Department of Mathematics, University of Hyderabad

Integrated Masters in Mathematics (Bachelors + Masters)

First Class with Distinction (GPA -8.8/10.0)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

05/2018 – 05/2019 Mathematician - Data Scientist

MyCol – Circle of Life Healthcare Private Limited

The circle of life healthcare private limited works in building Artificial Intelligence and

Machine Learning Models to solve problems in healthcare.

AWARDS & HONORS

05/2023 **2023** William K Estes Summer Research Award

An award given by the Psychology Department to identify and encourage individuals

with a potential for computational modeling.

05/2021 Computational Modeling Award in Applied Cognition

An award given by the Cognitive Science Society for the best applied cognitive modeling

paper at the annual meeting:

Improving Medical Image Decision Making by Leveraging Metacognitive Processes and

Representational Similarity

08/2020 Vanderbilt Psychology Scholarship

An award given in the Psychology department for outstanding performance for the year

08/2019 – 07/2022 Vanderbilt University Graduate Student Scholarship

The Vanderbilt Graduate Student Fellowship is guaranteed financial support from the Vanderbilt University. This competitive scholarship is meant to fund doctoral candidates for research and tuition during their stay in the university. The award was relinquished upon moving to Indiana University in 2022.

JRF - Mathematical Sciences

The junior research fellowship is a highly selective grant that is awarded to students in India through a competitive examination. It provides funding for them to conducted research in any nationally funded laboratory and for their graduate education.

08/2014-05/2018 **KVPY**

The Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana (KVPY) is an on-going National Program of Fellowship in Basic Sciences funded by Department of Science and Technology, India. It has a highly competitive selection procedure with only approximately 50 students being selected for it across all sciences. It provides a generous fellowship for students during their studies and encourages research activity by providing an annual contingency grant.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

08/2022 – Present Graduate Student

Computational Decision Making Lab, Indiana University

Dr. Jennifer Trueblood

Computational Models of Decision Making, Wisdom of the Crowd Aggregation Algorithms, Medical Image Decision Making, Food Decision Making, Multiattribute

Choice, Attention

08/2019 –08/2022 Graduate Student

Computational Decision Making Lab, Vanderbilt University

Dr. Jennifer Trueblood

Computational Models of Decision Making, Wisdom of the Crowd Aggregation Algorithms, Medical Image Decision Making, Food Decision Making, Multiattribute

Choice, Attention

05/2017 – 05/2019 Mathematical Modeler / Data Scientist

MyCol – Healthcare Pvt Ltd.

Mudit Kapoor

A startup that used machine learning to improve healthcare

08/2017 – 05/2018 Research Assistant

Department of Mathematics, University of Hyderabad

Convexity and Applications

08/2016 Research Assistant (Astronomy)

Department of Astronomy, MANUU

Priya Hasan

05/2016 Research Assistant (Cryptography)

Center for Security Theory and Algorithmic Research, IIIT Hyderabad

Kannan Srinathan

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Hasan, E., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A. C., Stratton, C., & Trueblood, J. S. (2023). Harnessing the wisdom of the confident crowd in medical image decision-making. *Decision* https://doi.org/10.1037/dec0000210

Hasan, E., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A. C., Stratton, C., & Trueblood, J. S. (2022). Improving Medical Image Decision-Making by Leveraging Metacognitive Processes and Representational Similarity. *Topics in Cognitive Science*. https://doi.org/10.1111/tops.12588

[Won the Computational Modeling Prize in Applied Cognition Category from the Cognitive Science Society]

Hasan, E., & Trueblood, J. S. (2022). Representational Smoothing to Improve Medical Image Decision Making. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society* (Vol. 44, No. 44).

PUBLICATIONS IN PREPARATION

Hasan, E., Duhaime, E., Trueblood J. S., (In Prep) Performance Based Selection and Weighting for Wisdom of the Crowds in Medical Image Decision Making

Hasan, E., Owens, N., Trueblood J. S. (Under Review) A Registered Report on presentation factors that influence the attraction effect *Judgment and Decision Making*.

CONFERENCE POSTERS AND TALKS

2023	Hasan, E., & Trueblood, J. (2023). The Role of Salience-Driven Attention on Multialternative Multiattribute Choice. Abstract published at MathPsych/ICCM/EMPG 2023. Via <u>mathpsych.org/presentation/1203</u> .
2022	Hasan, E., & Trueblood, J. (2022). Representational Smoothing to Improve Medical Image Decision Making. In <i>Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society</i> (Vol. 44, No. 44).
2022	Hasan, E., & Trueblood, J. (2022). Denoising and Debiasing Medical Image Decisions using Representational Smoothening. <i>Annual Meeting of the Society of Mathematical Psychology</i>
2022	Hasan, E., & Trueblood, J. (2022) The Wisdom of the Confident Crowd in Medical Image Decision-making. <i>Annual Meeting of the Society for Judgment and Decision Making</i>
2022	Hasan, E., Duhaime, E., Sekhar, T., Trueblood J. S., Improving Medical Image Classification using Wisdom of the Crowds. <i>Annual Meeting of the Psychonomic Society</i>

2021 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A., Stratton, C. Leveraging Representational Similarity to Improve Medical Image Decision Making Society for Judgment and Decision Making [Accepted as a Talk] 2021 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A., Stratton, C. Representational Denoising for Improving Medical Image Decision Making NeurIPS Workshop on Human and Machine Decision Making https://sites.google.com/view/whmd2021/home 2021 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A., Stratton, C. Improving Medical Image Decision Making by Leveraging Representational Similarity Society for Mathematical Psychology [Accepted as a Talk] 2021 Hasan E. Learning Multiattribute Choice in an Unknown Environment Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality at Max Plank Institute 2021 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A., Stratton, C. Improving Medical Image Decision Making by Similarity Based Aggregation **Psychonomics** 2021 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S., Eichbaum, Q., Seegmiller, A., Stratton, C. Improving Medical Image Decision Making by Leveraging Metacognitive Processes and Representational Similarity Proceedings of the Cognitive Science Society 2020 Hasan, E., Trueblood J.S. Defining a grammar for strategies in Multi-attribute Choice. Society for Mathematical Psychology. 2020 Hasan, E., Eichbaum, O., Daniels, P., Trueblood J.S. Wisdom of the Crowds for Naturalistic Image Categorization and Decision Making. Virtual Psychonomics

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2022	The Science of Choice	- Assistant Instructor
2022	Introduction to Statistics	- Assistant Instructor
2020, 2021	Behavioral Decision Making	g – Teaching Assistant
2020	Human Sexuality	 Teaching Assistant
2019	General Psychology	– Teaching Assistant

STUDENTS MENTORED

Ke Lai Honors Student Computational Decision Making Lab (2021 – 2023)

[Now a PhD Student at Duke]

Nicole Owens Research Assistant Computational Decision Making Lab. (2020-2021)

Helena Khalif High School Student Computational Decision Making Lab. (2020-2021)

GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Teaching of Psychology

Philosophy of Cognitive Science

Readings at the Interface of Machine Learning and Cognitive Science

Computational Models of Attention

Emotions

Scientific Writing

Human Cognition

Models of Human Memory

Developmental Psychology

Computational Neuroscience of Vision

Computation Cognitive Modeling

Computational Neuroscience

Bayesian Cognitive Modeling

Psychological Measurement

Introduction to Cognitive Science